When you have the sacrum, when you have the whole notochordal process, this wave that descends,
with this point of support, it creates this notochordal process.
And it is this notochordal process that directly induces an impulse
on the neural plate,
which means it will orient, organize this force on the plate
neural.
You can already see that over three days, you see, the growth...
this embryo that is forming, with one thing we notice, it is the descent,
so to speak,
if you will, of my Hensen node, in relation to the overall growth of the embryo,
here,
here, and already we can see, you see, the beginning of a neural groove
that appears
here, you see, with already the pharyngeal membrane and
the cloacal membrane taking shape, you see.
We see that we have my process, our body here.
We see the importance already of my neural plate that begins
to curve like this.
In the end, it will really form a significant groove
with a lateral, fluidic reorganization that is important.
It happens synchronously.
Because at the moment I already have my neural groove that...
is starting to form, laterally, immediately, there’s a fluidic organization
that takes shape, little by little, appearing as what we will call fine
capillary
aortic, which means that for there to be a lateral fluidic process, the
components
are respected, meaning that I need a trajectory, I need particles,
I need vacuolizations and metabolic concentrations that are present in this
and that will create a lateral vascular trajectory.
So at the same time I have my tube that is closing little by little,
and also laterally I have a
vascular trajectory in the mesoderm.
At the same moment that I have this phenomenon happening,
above, it should be noted that I have my amniotic cavity.
My amniotic cavity contains fluid.
This neural plate starts to form a tube, gradually a groove,
my amniotic fluid is integrated into the
neural tube,
just as it happens simultaneously below, with the integration of my external coelom into
To the point that at the moment my neural tube closes completely,
meaning the anterior neuropore and the posterior neuropore are closed,
I have the complete integration of the external coelom.
So I have both a visceral cavity, I have an abdominal
cavity forming,
and a cerebral cavity that is also closing. This happens at the same time, on the 28th day,
a synchronicity. Then there is a magical moment that occurs, a moment
when we have the
first time, we have the encounter of this closure. With
this integration, we have
forming here, my aortas, my notochords, it
is a tissue that will also surround,
in metabolic retention fields. We will see this a bit more
later. I try to make
the killer of this killer. For us, as osteopaths, it is interesting,
it is to see
these phenomena that happen at a distance, but at the same time, in another
space, but in the same time.
The precursor of this neural groove is the notochord.
When you have this closure of this notochord,
you have here what we call basic molecular levels
that will manifest to precisely
reduce the growth speed here.
You see what we call this phenomenon here which is sonic hedgehog
that will intervene here.
which is a process that will work on the dorsalization of the system,
then you have what we call bone morphogenetic proteins, which are here,
and then you also have what we call the neural crest cells that will intervene
here,
which are morphogenetic manifestations,
molecular, to retrieve this dynamic.
This means that the movement...
that we observe, which has been described by, among others, Blechschmidt or other authors,
is encountered with phenomena of inhibition or induction on the
basic molecular phenomena of a genetic type.
Therefore, what we observe is that the notochord will influence,
in the sense that the cells that are here will have more of an inductive phenomenon.
So, they become...
in relation to my notochord, a point of support.
This is information that will be quite important later,
with all these phenomena, we could say,
that will participate in neurulation,
which are these molecular phenomena, of a genetic, protein type,
to influence the system.
This will first influence my ventral midline, it will
cause by this phenomenon the dorsal midline.
The dorsal midline, through its growth, will re-influence the
anterior midline phenomenon.
So I end up with a ventral, dorsal, and anterior midline.
And all of this, are phenomena that are ultimately also molecular.
We find, you see, BMPs of type 4, 7,
that will participate in the dorsalization, at this level.
The 4s that will participate in the anterior orientation towards the ventral midline.
All of this, are molecular fields that are explained,
that we find on a scientific level,
which explain the program, if you will,
and which are also organized at this level.
So, this means that it is the movement...
that will reorient.
So genes are not the engine
for development.
It’s the environment, it’s the force
surrounding it. One might almost say it’s
a mechanical event at the start.
It’s the development
of your basic, neurochemical consciousness.
On a practical level,
do we find this level and how?
First there are two things.
The important thing is to know,
to try to discover as best as possible the environment.
in which your patient evolves. That is already the first step to understand your patient.
I especially give back the notochordal axis. I come back to it because it is the reference.
And then, I will free as best as possible the almost fluidic side
of your brain,
giving it back and looking at the sand to remove the dehydrated grounds for example.
There are energetically dehydrated areas.
There are programs that do not open, and help these programs if they need to open or
have opened.
We will still work on a level, it's a level of the very first moment of closure
of your tube.
There, that was the question.
And we will do work on that, because we will look for where it is located in the body.
And that’s where we'll rebalance the nervous system.
That is, your sympathetic and parasympathetic system.
And that is very important, and I will explain how we get there.
We hold well here these 3 meters.
My ectodermal tissue with its epithelial cells.
You know that this movement is induced by my notochord via molecular processes.
You notice that the lateral part grows faster and that it will form
this groove.
And there, we are already starting to distinguish the appearance of
cells that will form.
my neural tube,
which means the entire part
of the spinal canal
and of the brain.
And then we will see laterally here
cells that will form
the epidermal epithelial tissue,
the skin,
and we will see appearing
on the side here
another structure
that will be very, very important,
that we can still consider
as a fourth tissue.
what we call the bud of the neural crest tissues, which
is here.
Cells here in red, cells here in blue,
cells here in blue.
Not only does the neural tube close,
and it will have taken in its interior,
amniotic fluid.
Laterally, I will see here the cells
that will come here, which will be called neural crest cells,
that will form the entire peripheral nervous system
and also will make important connections with what we call the mesoderm
later
to form ectomesenchymal tissues.
like the face, the bones of the skull, etc.
The neural crest is a migration,
like a field of aspiration of rhombencephalic neural crests
of types 1, 2, 3, 4, to form the entire facial system.
When we talk about rhombencephalon, it means that at one point,
the brain, in its cephalic part, here, will form what we call
the forebrain, the midbrain, and the hindbrain.
These are three small vesicles.
But each of them, on their line here, also creates a crest like this, called
the neural crest,
and that will be found, being like drawn towards the
anterior part to form, for example, all your viscerocranial structures.
It should be noted that the tissue that is here, all of this, is not the same tissue that is here.
This is neural crest.
This is pure epidermis. So this means that it is a tissue here that is informed
within your body, that is both a tissue that
informs and is informed. It receives information and can transmit it, but also from the core to the periphery, from the periphery to the core.
You have sensors here, for example, on atmospheric pressure, the
light that...
you receive informs you, it’s first blue which means it’s
ectoderm, but this ectoderm, at the phase where it receives
the information here
of the manotocorp through molecular planes
of a protein-genetic type
the information here does not grow, so the cells here, the tissue we can say
that we will observe that it will give three types of different cells
The cells that will form only the neural tube, laterally,
here, at the tube, that will form what we call the neural crests and even more
here, that will form the epidermal epiblast.
So, the skin, the neural tube, the crests.
We will talk about it because it will give a lot, a lot of things in the body.
It really needs to be considered as a massive tissue, all your nervous system.
peripheral, everything is pexus mesenteric, parts at the level of the face,
at the level
of the nails, at the level of the teeth, at the level of the eyes, at the level of the tongue, it really is
a... and it will mix with mesoderm to form
ectomesenchyme.
Now we add a simple element here.
First, I still have my notochord.
I still have my notochord.
Secondly, here around, I have an amniotic cavity, so there is liquid.
In this liquid, it contains building proteins, which are
proteins among others for structuring.
This means that the liquid here is found both here, but
around, I forgot to draw one thing here,
that now here, I have...
And the tissue that has closed, we call the skin tissue.
So this means that the liquid that is here, inside,
and you also have liquid that is here outside.
And it’s the same liquid.
That’s why in certain writings, we describe the quality of skin.
The quality of skin expresses the quality...
of the cerebrospinal fluid in depth, cerebrospinal fluid,
you have the arterial system, you have the venous system, and
you have the lymphatic system.
These are the major important liquids, you also have other liquids like the synovial system,
or others, etc.
This is the master, this is the liquid that knows, this is the liquid that gives movement,
the liquid that cleans here, and this is the trash. It is the knowing liquid.
It was there, it was there very early. There was a liquid that was
before it. This is the one that will form the digestive tube, and
that will no longer be a liquid,
it will be a cavity.
The blastocoel, the first cavity that will appear, and then we saw at one point
that I answer to the first.
And then you have a second chamber that will appear, it is the amniotic cavity.
After that, you would have a third chamber that appears, which will be the speed
of growth
differential between the blood and the periphery of your implanted embryo.
This will create a space between your blastocoel cavity
and will form the external coelom
and the amniotic cavity, the vitelline cavity.
And the vitelline cavity, at one point, it will...
be taken back into your digestive system
to form your digestive tube.
So there will be a link, at one point,
that will be made with the amniotic fluid
and this cavity, because the child
will drink at one point this amniotic fluid,
it will integrate
into its body, it will
cluster, meaning
that it will inform itself from
autocrine, paracrine,
so that each time it knows where it is. Why?
Because at one point it will have a pre-urine
that will be emitted,
that is to say to go
into its amniotic cavity from, after the 28th day,
once the tube is about to close unless you do some racing in your brain,
you will have to eliminate that, so after the 28th day you will eliminate a bit of your first priorities
and it will create a support in terms of terrain, a link with your
aortic system
and then at the same time you will see and thus you will know where you are in your development.
It informs itself like that.
You have this level here we call SHH, which
is really a genetics, the sonic hedgehog, which is really important,
the cams, adhesion molecules at the neuronal level,
with a whole important complex we call the cadherin complexes.
They are all attached, it’s often calcium, that’s why we talk about
specific calcium ions working in the adherents.
That’s why we call them cadherins, calcium inside.
I have this groove, I have the cephalic part, the caudal part,
and then at one point, boom, the first moment it closes.
So if we look at an embryo, at this stage, the part
cephalic is very large compared to...
the caudal part
if now I have this moment here of closure
I already know a little bit
the dimension of my embryo
I know the relationships
I have practically the whole head
and all the trunk
all this corresponds to the cephalic part
all this corresponds to the part of the trunk
where it would be
now
In the tissue that is present here, where is this closure.
We are no longer at the tip of our cortex, we are under the nervous system.
The notochord is below, here.
We are between forebrain, midbrain, hindbrain.
Above and below the foramen magnum.
At the moment when the spinal canal begins, that is, at the level of C0-C1,
and well there, you find yourself in the lower part, here.
This is the part here where I could say where I find myself below the foramen magnum,
to the left and to the right.
This is the part where I find myself above the foramen magnum, to the left and to the right.
What makes it be at this level?
Remember the algorithm and why.
If it closes early, it means it develops faster.
Because it eats more.
Why does it eat more?
Because it receives more.
It’s my heart's pulsation that does that.
There, we’ll put in this movement, we will integrate all the metabolic fields
for ectomenix,
all the important relationship at the level of my building
morphological, proteins,
finally all these structuring proteins, the growth factors.
We exceed all that.
I will animate this image.
I have my amniotic cavity.
I have my vitelline cavity, between the two I have my trichermic disc,
then I will take this trichermic disc, I
will remove the amniotic cavity, remove the vitelline cavity, and turn
the upper face towards you, and we will see the movement of my tube
neural that comes to close, and we will see the first moment where I have this impulse.
And we will use this first encounter between the
left and the right, if you will, at the level of your neural tube on the anterior plane,
as a therapeutic tool to do a rebalancing of the system.
The posterior neuropore
and the anterior neuropore.
8 faces
with the cardiac zone
small anatomy question
Philippe this is for you
once the
anterior neuropore
is closed. What anatomical structure becomes
The lamina terminalis!
Do you see the cardiac zone here?
What he will have is a pulse on this cell.
Let’s go, let’s go.